now in the United States the first CIA
officer ever to be jailed for leaking
information is about to discover how
long he's to spend in prison CIA veteran
John kyaku has pleaded guilty to
revealing the name of an agent who was
involved in waterboarding Terror suspect
but his supporters say he's been pursued
for blowing the whistle on torture who's
our Washington correspondent Matt
Fry can I be honest with you
I am bad
news I'm not your friend I'm not going
to help you I'm going to break
you any
questions Zero Dark 30 the movie based
on the true story of how America's most
elusive foe was tracked down and killed
the film doesn't skirt around the fact
that Osama Bin Laden would not have been
found without information extracted by
torture we'll never find him
and the film itself would never have
been made without information leaked by
someone in Authority this is a movie The
White House wants you to see I became
the chief of counterterrorist operations
in Pakistan uh where I helped capture
many dozens of al-Qaeda terrorist
suspects including Abu zua who at the
time was thought to be the third ranking
official in al-Qaeda when John Kaku
talks about his Feats he sounds at first
like one of the cia's hero but listen
more
closely after we captured abuaba I spent
uh several days as his soul minder while
the agency figured out what to do with
him and what they ended up doing with
him was to take him to a secret prison
and to torture him
mercilessly uh including to waterboard
him 83 times we need to know the names
of the people water boarding an enhanced
interrogation technique or in plain
English torture systematically used by
the CIA after 9/11 kyaku was the first
agent to go public about it and is
paying the price what are you going to
do he's gone from decorated spy to
disgrace convict don't kick
me soon he won't be playing with his
kids in their Suburban Washington Garden
he will serve a 30mon sentence the first
American ever to go behind bars for
waterboarding and not for having
committed it but for having blown the
whistle on it none of the high pressure
situations I ever found myself uh in
overseas working in counterterrorism
including two uh attempts on My Life by
different terrorist groups uh could
compare with the the notion of the
entire weight of the US government
coming down on Meo will be closed uh no
later than one year from now remember
this day one of his freshly minted
presidency four years later guantan Bay
remains open for business there we go
yes this Administration has stopped
waterboarding but it's also gone after
leakers like John kako with a
Vengeance Barack Obama was elected on a
platform of transparency and change and
has led the worst clamp down on
whistleblowers in history in your
opinion torture or not
torture I think yes torture John kako
broke the cia's Code of Silence he went
public on waterboarding called it
torture and then cashed in on the
publicity with a book and lectures here
you are sir but that in itself wasn't
enough to trigger an
investigation this was his revelation of
the identity of undercover agents
involved in the torture of inmates like
these at Guantanamo Bay got him into
trouble with the Obama Administration
first there were spying charges but they
were then dropped after a deal in which
kako pled guilty to revealing the name
of One agent your client did after all
plead guilty to revealing the name of an
undercover operative that is a no no
yeah he plead guilty to confirming the
identity of a torturer the
administration would say that if you
allow such leaks to go ahead the
clandestine Services can no longer
operate in a clandestine way do you buy
that argument at all I do not the
government is the biggest leaker in the
United States this Administration seems
to sanction leaks and indiscretion
whenever it suits them for instance
telling the makers of zero duck 30 some
of the details of the the raid on Usama
Bin Laden or indeed providing details of
drone attacks and targeted killings to
the New York Times in the middle of last
year's heated election campaign at the
same time it's a fact that the Obama
Administration has prosecuted more
leakers than all other administrations
put together so where does that
contradiction leave this
administration's much touted belief in
openness and
transparency Matt Fry Channel 4 News
Washington t